<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Apology for the failures charg'd on the Reverend Mr. George Walker's printed account of the late siege of Derry in a letter to the undertaker of a more accurate narrative of that siege.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24184</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08043498</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08043498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40765</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40765)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1221:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Apology for the failures charg'd on the Reverend Mr. George Walker's printed account of the late siege of Derry in a letter to the undertaker of a more accurate narrative of that siege.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walker, George, 1645?-1690. --  True account of the siege of Londonderry.</term>
               <term>Londonderry (Northern Ireland) --  History --  Siege, 1689.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40765:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE FAILURES Charg'd on the Reverend Mr. George Walker's PRINTED ACCOUNT Of the late <hi>Siege of Derry,</hi> IN A LETTER to the Undertaker of a more Accurate Narrative of that SIEGE.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40765:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40765:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY FOR THE FAILURES Charg'd on the Reverend Mr. George Walker's PRINTED ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Siege of Derry.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOUR Inventory of thoſe momentous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes you offer to demonſtrate in the late Printed Account of the Siege of <hi>Derry,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40765:3"/>with your Reflections on 'em was ſurvey'd by ſome of our Club, Men of approv'd Prudence and Moderation, who alſo pay a great deference to the celebrated Mr. <hi>Walker:</hi> Their una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Verdict is, You Publiſh theſe Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions, with the accurate Journal of that Siege, which by this time you expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: This they judge of abſolute Neceſſity, as being the moſt appoſit medium to give reſurrection to the Memory of as well the yet living, as the lately expir'd, of that great Body of Northern <hi>Scots,</hi> (of late the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Papiſts, and Envy of an ambitious Party in <hi>Ireland</hi>) which the above Account endeavours to extinguiſh, and bury with ſome ingenious Scars in the Grave of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Oblivion.</p>
            <p>I had ſent you this Commiſſion laſt Week, had it not been recall'd upon a Motion made, and carried by the major Vote, that no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Narrative on this Subject, how accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſoever, be Printed, but with a <hi>Salvo</hi> of the Honour, with which his perſonal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, auſpicious Conduct, in his Government of <hi>Derry,</hi> with his Majeſty's gracious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance thereof, have already inveſted Mr. <hi>Walker.</hi> This Vote we took for an embaraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as inſuperable as <hi>Kilmore Boom;</hi> till laſt Night one of our Number undertook
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40765:3"/>to remove it, by a juſt Apology he ſaid he had provided for Collonel <hi>Walker,</hi> abridg'd in a Letter to you, intended chiefly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie ſome dangerous Miſtakes of yours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that excellent Perſon: The Letter being read and approv'd, I here preſent you with the Inſcription, Preface, Subſcription omitted.</p>
            <p>On behalf of the Collonel I offer this double Plea: The Firſt, That 'tis his Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, not his Sin, to be miſtaken for the Author of thoſe Miſrepreſentations, with which you charge his Narrative. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, To diſcover their genuine Parents, with ſome of the occult Cauſes of their Production in this juncture. The Arguments evincing the former, are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Narrative is guilty of manifeſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation of the prime Rule of Hiſtory: (<hi>viz.</hi> That nothing be inſerted for truth, but that whoſe intrinſick Evidence commands the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er's belief, or borrow'd, renders it at leaſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible.) Your Animadverſions preſent us with many Inſtances of this kind; the exact Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal will with more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Account peremptorily, and very immodeſtly, confronts the Verbal Narratives
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40765:4"/>Collonel <hi>Walker</hi> occaſionally gave of that Siege, all along his Journey, before his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at <hi>London;</hi> very eminent inſtances whereof I have already tranſmitted both from <hi>Scotland</hi> and ſome remoter parts of <hi>England,</hi> which I am ready to produce, when they may prove ſerviceable to Mr. <hi>Walker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This Narrative pretends to give the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Tranſactions in that Garriſon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Collonel <hi>Walker</hi> was neither Spectator nor Actor, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the four Months that paſs'd between the firſt locking the Gates, and his Arrival at <hi>Derry;</hi> Collonel <hi>Walker</hi> having neither in <hi>Derry</hi> furniſh'd himſelf with a Journal of that time, nor conſulted thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who alone were qualified to give him a full Account of all the Proceedings in that interval; though he knew 'em to be in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> while he prepar'd his Narrative, and had the opportunity of daily Converſe with 'em.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Narrative quite diveſts the firſt and principal Actors of the Honour of that firſt Service, without which this Narrative had beeu a Non-entity; in ſpecial, Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor <hi>Cairns,</hi> who declar'd for the then Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion; who form'd the Multitude into Companies after
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40765:4"/>locking the Gates: Transferrs it on thoſe whoſe only claim to it is the Narrator's Bounty, or, if you pleaſe, his Charity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This Narrative tranſmitts not half that imperfect Journal (now in <hi>London</hi>) whence 'tis borrowed; and (which ſeems at leaſt very indecent) is ſo far from emblazoning the matchleſs Gallantry of even the chief Commanders, (as well as thoſe firſt Actors above hinted) that it either paſſes over in ſilence their Actions, or their moſt remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Circumſtances, which would prove its chief Ornament; a due Account whereof would command the Reader's Admiration, and eternize the Actor's Memory, eminent Inſtances whereof we expect from your Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative. Now beſides the Diſparagement ſuch failures reflect on the Hiſtorian, I doubt it will be ſound an arduous Undertaking to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for 'em to the ſurviving Relations and Poſterity of thoſe Hero's, (eſpecially the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Collonel <hi>Baker</hi>) whoſe inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Sorrows under their irreparable loſs might be ſomewhat alleviated by their reviewing in the Monuments of unſuſpected Hiſtory the renowned Lives and glorious Tranſits of their deceaſed Relations.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The intire Texture of this Narrative diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40765:5"/>its being contriv'd under the Conduct of mortal Prejudice againſt the Northern <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyterians: Notorious in three equally groundleſs and immodeſt Calumnies. 1. Againſt Mr. <hi>Osborn,</hi> the Vindication of whoſe Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will merit room in your Narrative. 2. In Mr. <hi>Hewſon</hi>'s being plac'd in the ſame Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory with Mr. <hi>Osborn,</hi> though many thouſands yet alive in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> are ready to teſtiſie, nor does himſelf deny it, that <hi>Hewſon</hi> was diſcarded ſome Years ago by the Northern Presbyters, and to this day lyes under Sentence of Depoſition paſs'd on him by all their Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries for notorious Scandals; is no more a Member of Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Communion than of Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s. 3. Moſt eminently, in not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting thye Names of the ſeven Non-conſorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters in <hi>Derry,</hi> under pretence of want of Information, after a Liſt of their Names was put into Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Hand, by the ſame Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman now in <hi>London,</hi> from whom Mr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> had the Diary.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This Narrative gives Collonel <hi>Walker</hi> the firſt Figure in Martial Exploits, in which I preſume his Modeſty will own, he had ſeveral Equals, ſome Superiors in <hi>Derry,</hi> beſides Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>yiBaker;</hi> of which ſome are on tip-toe to give him demonſtration, (which they ſay his Narrative exacts from 'em) did they not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40765:5"/>his Gown more than they fear his Sword. It inveſts him ſolely with the whole Conduct, and that in the quality firſt of Chief, after of ſole go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor: whereas thouſands yet ſurviving confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently averr, he had not been Aſſiſtant Governor, but by Collonel <hi>Baker</hi>'s Intereſt, much leſs chief, had nor that Gentleman's Modeſty in comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> with the Precedency in their joint Subſcriptions, given him the opportunity of converting Collonel <hi>Baker</hi>'s civil Ceremony into a ſacred, and very ſignificant to the Churches Service, of which more anon; thus, <hi>Cedunt arma togae;</hi> thus he carried the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, firſt of <hi>Chief,</hi> ever after of <hi>Sole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of Derry,</hi> for whom the Garriſon intended neither.</p>
            <p>I have contented my ſelf at preſent with a bare alluſion to ſome Perſons and things in theſe Arguments, have ſtudiouſly avoided giving 'em due form and full ſtrength; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the deſerence I bear to Mr. <hi>VValker</hi>'s Perſon; partly becauſe this will fall properly within your Province in your intended Narrative. Suſſice it, they anſwer the end they are produced for, <hi>viz.</hi> To evince that an Hiſtory obnoxious to the heavy charge theſe Premiſes inſerr, can with no Modeſty vouch a Perſon of Mr. <hi>VValker</hi>'s Character for its genuine Author; ſome one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40765:6"/>of theſe taken ſingle, being of ſufficient force (much more the whole Conjunct) to blaſt the Credit of any Hiſtory what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. In ſumm, this Hiſtory bears no more reſemblance to the excellent Governour of <hi>Derry,</hi> than <hi>Simon Magus</hi> to <hi>Simon Peter:</hi> But if any be found ſo hardy as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt an Attaque upon either theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes or the Concluſion, pray Capitulate with 'em for a Ceſſation of Arms 'till your Narrative is Printed, and then I promiſe to give 'em Battle, if they pleaſe, before the Walls of <hi>Derry:</hi> Mean while I take leave of the firſt part of my Apology for the Collonel, and proceed to the ſecond; in my Conduct to which, I doubt not to make ſome Advantage of thoſe very Bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kad's by which you endeavour to prevent my Paſſage. The firſt, and I hope princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If it be an unpardonable Crime, to entitle Mr. <hi>VValker</hi> to thoſe Miſadventures of which you impeach his Narrative, what Hecatomb can attone for the bold Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the High and Sacred Dedication prefix'd to it? For a full Anſwer to this formidable Objection, (which will go a great way to compleat the Apology) I humbly offer to your ſecond thoughts, whether you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40765:6"/>are not in equity oblig'd to allow in the Perſon of Mr. <hi>George VValker,</hi> the diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating qualities of late Governour of <hi>Derry,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Donnogh-moor:</hi> In the former you are to conſider him in a Martial Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, in the latter an Eccleſiaſtick: In the former he own'd no Superiour terrene but his Sovereign, in the latter many, in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial his Dioceſan: In the former he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thouſands without controll, in the latter he muſt obey, not diſpute the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of his Superiours: In the former he ſought for King <hi>VVilliam,</hi> Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with you Presbyterians, avoiding all diſcrimination of the Church and Kirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>party, (which then would have proved fatal) in the latter he was oblig'd to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his Narrative under the Conduct and Command of his Eccleſiaſtick Governours: conſequently in a Method might equally ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Churches Honour and Intereſt, and diſſerve thoſe of the Kirk. If you would know who theſe Eccleſiaſticks are, to whom you owe the moſt injurious miſtakes in this Narrative, pray enquire who that very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Prelate from <hi>Ireland</hi> is, who went as far as <hi>Barnet</hi> to meet Collonel <hi>VValker,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd him into his own Coach, conducted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40765:7"/>him to <hi>London;</hi> under whoſe menage Mr. <hi>VValker</hi> was obſerv'd to act while he was preparing his Narrative. This Biſhop with ſome others of his Club can inform you beſt of any. I ſhall then adventure to give you their Names, when the Act of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> as it reſpects that Order, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd, which I dare affirm, will be found the Intereſt of both Church and State. 'Till then, I beg your Excuſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> If you further Object, it ſuits not over well with Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, to paſs ſuch things in his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory as have nothing to ſupport their Credit, but the bare Command of his Eccleſiaftick Superiors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> I confeſs all the Diſtinctions in <hi>Scotus</hi> your ſubtle Countrey-man muſt leave this Objection unanſwer'd, upon the Principles of you Presbyterians, whoſe nigh thirty Years Sufferings, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Indigency, you owe to your oppoſing your private Coſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40765:7"/>as the proximate Rule of your Actions, to the conſcience and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of your Superiors. But upon Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Principles 'tis eaſily blown off: For though our Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to Infallibility, in determining Points of Faith, yet ſhe pretends, and I hope juſtly, to uncontrollable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to her Commands over her infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Clergy, and to the dictates of the publick Conſcience over the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; and therefore though Mr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> might modeſtly concert the Truth of thoſe Paſſages, which bear not ſo much as its imperfect Colour, yet might he at no hand diſpute inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em, if his Superior require it. Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> could not forget, though you may, that Modern Doctrine, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry edifying to the Embracers as well as Inventers of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That where the Matter of my Superior's Command is doubeful, (as undoubtedly in this Caſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40765:8"/>it was) his Command makes it my undoubted Duty to obey: Obedience to my Superior being my undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Duty, complying with my doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſcience being a buſineſs of very doubtful and dangerous Event: Though I'm very apt to believe, had ſome men among us foreſeen it would ever be their own fate to take San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary in the private (and as they call'd it) pretended Conſcience, (which is the pittiable, I ſay not ridiculous misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of all thoſe of our Clergy who now refuſe to Swear Allegiance to the beſt of Kings) they would heretofore have leſs ridicul'd it. But to compleat Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Vindication, and the ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Objection, I'm forc'd to reveal an <hi>Horribile Secretum,</hi> whoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery by Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> had prov'd as fatal as <hi>Calvin</hi>'s <hi>Horribile Decretum,</hi> (on which you know who among us betray'd horrible Ignorance of Latin
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40765:8"/>as well as Divinity) 'tis this. On that memorable Evening of lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Derry</hi>-Gates, in an Aſſembly of the chief Citizens, conſulting their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, then preſent, whether they ſhould receive a Popiſh Regiment of King <hi>James</hi>'s Army, then approaching to ſeize the Garriſon for that King's Service, the good Biſhop having long before ebib'd the Doctrine of Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, gravely exhorted them to the Affirmative; aſſuring them (though with the loſs of the Garriſon for King <hi>William</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion) they ſhould thereby become a Victim to the ſanguinary Cut-throats, yet the Loyalty of their Obedience to their ONLY lawful Sovereign, would abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly recompenſe their deepeſt Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: Upon which one <hi>Irwin,</hi> (I'm told) a young Presbyterian <hi>Scot,</hi> cry'd out, <hi>My Lord, your Doctrine's very good, but we can't now hear you out;</hi> and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40765:9"/>getting the Keys, with ſome others of his Fellows, lock'd all the Gates, a few Minutes before the two formoſt Companies demanded entrance in King <hi>James</hi>'s Name: Can you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, had Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> been <hi>ſui juris,</hi> his Narrative would not have afforded at leaſt one Line to the Reſolution, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, and ineſtimable ſerviceableneſs of this Action? without which, this Account of the following Gallantry diſplay'd on that Stage had probably iſſu'd in a ſecond Hiſtory of Maſſacres, exceeding thoſe of 41. But to return to the Biſhop; he finding his Doctrine the oftner repeated, leſs credited by Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebel <hi>Jack Presbyter,</hi> left the City ſome days after to the diſloyal Whiggs.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Sir,</hi> make Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Caſe your own, and ſuppoſe your Merit (as indeed his is) above the Deanry of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> vacant, (by Mr. <hi>Manby</hi>'s exchanging
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40765:9"/>the Communion of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for the more encharming Imbraces, as he pretended, of the Mother-Church) and the Biſhoprick too, by the Biſhop's Abdication: Yet upon your Canonical Obedience tell me, could you do leſs in Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Circumſtances than cover this pernicious Counſel of your Dioceſan, which created Nature can't expiate, and aſſure your Sovereign, God intimates to the World the Church of <hi>England</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends and maintains their Majeſty's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and the Proteſtant Religion; and improve your Rhetorick to perſwade their Majeſties the Diſſenters are at beſt unſerviceable to either Intereſt. I hope, <hi>Sir,</hi> by this time you are ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Innocency in his Publiſhing the above Account. You Presbyterians diſtinguiſh between the Action and the Anomy, or Irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, which latter you ſay in the Original makes the ſin: You will alſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40765:10"/>grant that the bare Inſtrument is often blameleſs, when the principal efficient is very culpable: I plead for no more on behalf of this worthy Gentleman, and ſo conclude his Apology; though I heartily wiſh he had not given me the trouble, am perſwaded himſelf does, he had not given the occaſion to any to believe very applicable to him (ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of the Biſhops Coach) that Paſſage of the Satyriſt<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Juv.</hi> Sat. 10. <hi>lin.</hi> 278, <hi>ad lin.</hi> 282.</note> reſpecting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul <hi>Marius,</hi> (if the compariſon be not too mean for the Collonel's Merit,)
<q>
                  <l>— quod illo cive tuliſſet</l>
                  <l>Natura in terris, quid Roma beatius unquam,</l>
                  <l>Si — animam exhalaſſet opimam,</l>
                  <l>Cum de Teutonico vellet deſcendere curru?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40765:10"/>
            <p>I intended, my hand being in, to beſtow a caſt of my Office upon theſe Gentlemen, whoſe alone Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands could qualifie Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> to plead Not Guilty to your Charge; and to have aſſign'd the leading Reaſons of their exerting their Authority over him in this juncture: But being doubtful of their Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, I ſhall leave to themſelves that Province; mean while will furniſh you with ſome Queries, I'd have you lodge with 'em; to which, their Anſwers, whether Categorical or Equivocal, will diſcover theſe Reaſons, and peradventure what lies ſomewhat deeper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 1. Whether theſe Gentlemen, I mean the <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> Eccleſiaſtic Club; or if you pleaſe, Committee for the Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> were not ſollicitouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of the too great Figure the Northern <hi>Scots</hi> made for many years paſt? Being unqueſtionably the greateſt Body of Proteſtants in <hi>Europe,</hi> intirely united in Principle, Intereſt, Alliance and mutual Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; who, upon an Eſtimate made of their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber three years ſince, were found to amount to Eighty Thouſand Fighting Men<note n="‖" place="margin">Pray ſee for this the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly Penn'd Letter to the truly Honourable Sir <hi>Arthur Royden</hi> about that time.</note>; and upon a more exact ſince, to about a 1000000. Whether they were not ſufficient to have preſerved intire the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and by their aſſiſtance to the Engliſh in all other parts, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have ſav'd the whole Kingdom from being loſt, or before this time to have retriev'd it, without putting our King or Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> to any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40765:11"/>other charge than Arms, Ammunition, one Chief Commander, little or no Treaſure, had Arms been ſent 'em any time before <hi>March</hi> laſt? Whether the matchleſs Proweſs and Services of thoſe ſew <hi>Innis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killin</hi>-Men, with thoſe in the Garriſon of <hi>Derry,</hi> do not determine this <hi>Quere</hi> in the Affirmative?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 2. Whether, ſuppoſe Presbytery and Prelacy plac'd on a level, ſhare equally in the Favour of King and Parliament, with the Church-revenues and Dignities; every individual being left to his proper choice (all which Conditions I humbly conceive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>requiſit to the right ſtating the Queſtion) in that great Northern Body, the Tyth fall to the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s ſhare? I know who would venture a Pole, e're they yielded that: if the danger of incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Guilt of Sacrilege did not deter 'em.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 3. Whether theſe Gentlemen don't in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment determin the ſecond <hi>Query</hi> in the Negative? Since one of their Club, a Gentleman of great Senſe, as intelligent in Iriſh Affairs as any, upon the report of ſo many thouſands dying in <hi>Derry</hi> by Famine, ſpoke plainly among ſome of his Gown, what others would perhaps for State-reaſons have minc'd, <hi>viz. Twas no matter how many of them dy'd, for they were but a pack of Scots Presbyterians.</hi> And I'm perſwaded had Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> when he brought the Colonel to <hi>London,</hi> left the Parſon at <hi>Donnoh-moor,</hi> a pack of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians they had been ſtill. But pray deal gently with the young Man Mr. — for his Father's
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40765:11"/>ſake, who, as I have heard, was the moſt Scotiz'd Presbyterian Miniſter of the Engliſh Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 4. What Counſels, what Inſtruments may be juſtly charged with the unattoneable Guilt of retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conveyance of thoſe Arms and Ammunition (till the Seaſon was loſt) which might have ſav'd, or ſpeedily reduc'd <hi>Ireland?</hi> Not our moſt gracious Sovereign, whoſe Royal Propenſion, repeated Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Commands for the ſpeedy and effectual relieving the Proteſtants there, His Majeſties Royal Concern for the Delays of the Conveyance of theſe Succours, his Subjects of the firſt Figure atteſt, and the Rebels dreaded the event of, Not the Diſſenters, nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Conformiſts, both whoſe accurat accounts of the condition of <hi>Ireland</hi> were laſt Spring frequently confronted by Letters from <hi>Eutopia,</hi> till the doleful event diſcover'd the truth of the former, and Fiction of the latter. Not the City of <hi>London,</hi> whoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs to ſpare no Treaſure, or if need were, Hands, in that Service, whoſe unparallel'd Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and incredible Charge in maintaining diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Proteſtants from <hi>Ireland,</hi> as well all <hi>England</hi> over, as in the City of <hi>London,</hi> all of you that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any Sparks of Honour and Gratitude admire and Celebrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 5. Whether thoſe unaccounted (but not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable) baffles giv'n to the reliefs ſent to <hi>Derry,</hi> firſt by Colonel <hi>Coningham,</hi> &amp;c. and afterwards by — do not iſſue from the ſame Spring with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40765:12"/>the Delays mentioned in the next preceding <hi>Query?</hi> Whether the Romance of <hi>Kilmore Boom</hi> will attone for the loſs of thoſe Thouſands of Souls (near a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riad by this time) of immortal Memory, that periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Derry</hi> for want of thoſe Succours, Royal Bounty ſo amply provided, Royal Care order'd the ſpeedy and ſeaſonable conveyance of? But of this enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Boom at more leiſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 6. Whether ſome Men are not ſatisfy'd (I don't ſay endeavour) <hi>Ireland</hi> be entirely loſt, (tho themſelves have large Stakes there to loſe) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unreduc'd for ſome years, rather than Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters be employ'd in retrieving it, ſhare in the Rewards of that Service, make ſome Figure in their Country, be rendred capable of their Prince's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, of Honours and Offices in common with their Fellow-Subjects proportionably to their Merit? I'le exclude from this Category (and with their own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation) all the moderate Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> both Clergy and Laity; yet am ſure ſome ſuch Men there be. Theſe Gentlemen can perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture diſcover 'em.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 7. Whether, if all Proteſtant Subjects were equally forward with the Diſſenters for the Service of the King, Kingdoms, and Proteſtant Religion, the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Arrival in <hi>Ireland</hi> had not been effectually prevented? And beſides, either the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or retrieving of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Rebellion in <hi>Scotland</hi> had not been either prevented or cruſh'd in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40765:12"/>the Egg, as well as the execrable Plot in <hi>Edinburg,</hi> whoſe Origin, ſays ſome, is the ſame with that Kings Declaration, lately Printed in <hi>London,</hi> and diſperſed in <hi>England,</hi> and no body doubts, lies nearer <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> than <hi>Edinburgh?</hi> Whether if Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters had been entruſted with the Conduct, or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Service of the Fleet, they had not at leaſt guarded the Brittiſh Seas againſt the French Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, if not have given a good account of the French Fleet?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 8. Whether if his Majeſty were veſted with as unlimited Empire over the Hearts, Eſtates, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of all other Proteſtants in his Dominions, as of all the Diſſenting Proteſtants at home, and all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants abroad without exception, it would not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him the moſt Auguſt, moſt Potent, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably the moſt happy Monarch on Earth? As by natural Right, Perſonal Merit, Divine Diſpoſal he is already of all the Chriſtian Orb? Whether all Papiſts, and all other Perſons diſaffected to their Majeſties Sacred Perſons, Government, and Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had not before this been remov'd from King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Camp, and his Majeſties Service, unleſs they gave ſufficient Security of their peaceable and Loyal Behaviour? Whether one Diſloyal Diſſenter, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to the Government can be produc'd in their Majeſty's Dominions in this Reign? Whether Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Schomberg</hi> on the Head of 50000, or if need were, a 100000 Men, might not by this time make the Walls of <hi>Paris</hi> quake? If not in their Majeſty's
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40765:13"/>Name take peaceable poſſeſſion of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> and diſplay in the heart of <hi>Paris</hi> the Engliſh im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Banner? Whether his Majeſty would need any aid from any of his Allies to Suppreſs any Rebellion in his Dominions; or at all employ any Forreign Forces, except in extending his Empire beyond the <hi>Alps,</hi> &amp;c, or in both <hi>Indies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 9. What theſe Gentlemen will advance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Printing the C. Hiſtory of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the two laſt Reigns, almoſt ready for the Preſs? We'll give 'em City-Security to do 'em in it as much right, as Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s Narrative has done the Presbyterians wrong. We'll tell nothing but the Truth, though not the whole Truth, it being impoſſible to repreſent to the Life all the good Services (ſome being very ſecret) of ſome of the Biſhops, eſpecially the three Archbiſhops now living: whether to the Catholick Cauſe, in their zealous Eſpouſal and advance of the <hi>York</hi>-Intereſt, and thereby of the Iriſh Catholicks: Or to the Church, in their conferring of Livings and Eccleſiaſtic Dignities on the Inferiour Clergy, (whoſe Qualifications and Converſations the Hiſtorian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts for) in proportion to their Talent of railing genteelly at the Phanaticks. In their affronting, yea, ſilencing (ſome) of their own Clergy, for Preaching boldly the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt the Papiſts: In the Biſhops turning Informers to the Government againſt the Diſſenters, expoſing them to the Odium of the Government, contempt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: In their Perſecuting, Fining, Confining, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40765:13"/>them, <hi>cum multis aliis</hi>— The unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of the Printer drives the Hiſtorian to this involuntary Addreſs to theſe Gentlemen: For he ſays, he wont take for Printing this, being a large Folio, ten times the Sum he paid for Mr. <hi>Wr</hi>'s Copy; unleſs the two Iriſh Archbiſhops now in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> will promiſe <hi>Verbo Sacerdotis</hi> to take off nine parts of the Impreſſion for <hi>Ireland,</hi> the tenth being more than he hopes to have vent for in <hi>England.</hi> The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> he ſays is a poor Spiritual Prince; has receiv'd of our publick Fund of Charity to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs'd Proteſtants from <hi>Ireland,</hi> not above a 1000 <hi>l.</hi> that he can hear of; has in <hi>England</hi> not above 10000 <hi>l.</hi> in Bank, deſign'd for a Purchaſe; therefore expects his Brother Archbiſhop ſhould be bound with him.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Laſtly <hi>Quaeritur,</hi> Sir, of your ſelf, whether by this time you do not foreſee conſequence enough in any imaginable Anſwer may be given to theſe Queſtions for concluding it neceſſary in theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to have improv'd as they did, their Empire over Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> in this juncture; though they might foreſee the event ſomewhat prejudicial to him, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to your Party? I muſt alſo inform you, ſome of theſe Gentlemen are no leſs ſtudy'd in Politicks than in Divinity; the former being their conſtant, if not ſole buſineſs ever after Conſecration; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter only ſubſerves the former; which ſeldom hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, but when in a Sermon (the Quinteſſence of two or three years profound premeditation) the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40765:14"/>is to be gravely reminded of the Churches infinit Service to the State, above all poſſibility of a full reward; or to preſcribe to the Government ſome new method of hampering the Fanaticks, whom the Churches neither Grace nor Wiſdom could ever reclaim; who are never thankful for any of the Churches Bleſſings, neither for <hi>Oxford</hi>-Oaths, Five-mile-Acts, twenty pounds Fine <hi>per</hi> Month, Mouth-padlocks, Meal-tub-Plots, Iriſh Witneſſes, nor all the Devices of <hi>Old Nick</hi> himſelf, to reduce 'em to Canonical Obedience. You muſt further know, theſe Gentlemen bear a very Sympathizing Senſe of the Odium the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially ſome of the Biſhops have incurred from all Proteſtants abroad, and ſome of their own Communion at home, for their Ingratitude (to mention nothing higher, if higher may be) to our moſt gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, after having but a little before magnify'd him to the Stars, though ſtill below his Merit, as the only Saviour of their Lives under God, as well as Protector of their Eſtates and Dignities. Now the incomparable Sagacity of theſe Gentlemen diſcover'd an opportunity, and they had the Grace to improve it (the like having been never preſented before, perhaps never may again) of not only wiping off all this Reproach, but alſo of acquiring a greater Glory (and why not Reward too) to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than perhaps any modeſt Engliſh-man will challenge to the whole Nation; and all this by the Service (you know of whom, but) attributed to one of their undignify'd Clergy. Pray obſerve
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40765:14"/>the Modeſty of the Dedication — God Fights their Majeſty's Battels—but by the hand of the Church — Defends and maintains their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Intereſt and the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>I don't wonder this Myſtery ſhould not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily enter your Presbyterian Skull, ſince it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires equally with Tranſubſtantiation, a Head Abdicated of Reaſon and Five Senſes: my own Pate, though of ſomewhat a more Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick make than yours, has a deadly hard tug on't.</p>
            <p>For though I can (to magnifie the Service of our Church) allow you <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter Scots</hi> and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Diſſenters ſhould paſs for Powder-monkies of the Churches Army (except the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> men, whoſe hopes muſt not yet be quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn) and that half of the Earl of <hi>Angus</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould paſs for Cowards, (it being Canonico-Prelatically impoſſible, tho Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matico-Presbyterially certain, ſo deſpicable a handful of the deepeſt-dy'd-Kirk-Whiggs ſhould utterly defeat, without hopes of ever again ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying, our Churches Hoſt; conſiſting, very few excepted) of the Churches beſt Sons and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which the Sequel demonſtrates; for the Whigs there did not ſo much boaſt of the Victory, as the Tories here bewail'd the Diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiture.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40765:15"/>
            <p>Yet can I by no means yield, the renowned General <hi>Schomberg</hi> ſhould not make a Thumb at leaſt, and the <hi>Dutch, Germans,</hi> and <hi>Swiſſes</hi> he Commands (who were never ſeen to turn their Backs on any Enemy, but after Victory) ſhould not make one Finger more, of that invincible hand, that defends and maintains the King's Intereſt, and the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>It wants Confirmation, That the Fingers of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in the Face of their Enemy, are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed only in turning up their Muſtacho's, to teach <hi>Teague</hi> a more decent way of taking Snuſh, or in concerting the Antiquity of <hi>Min-Heir</hi> and <hi>Mounſieur,</hi> while the Hand of the Church is preparing Mandates, with a Preſent of Leaden Padderines to be ſent Poſt by the French and Iriſh to Saint <hi>Patrick</hi> in Purgatory.</p>
            <p>However, I doubt not theſe Gentlemen's fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal neceſſity, or pious Zeal for recovering the ſo-lately-decay'd Stock of the Churches Credit, will excuſe (if not hallow) their pious Fraud in thus managing Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> to moſt of the true Sons of the Church; and therefore I pray, it may to you; and ſo much the ſooner, becauſe this with the preceeding Apology for Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> removes all Letts to your Printing your deſign'd Narrative, except a Licenſe, which the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40765:15"/>above-named, upon your preſenting him with theſe Queries will infallibly procure.</p>
            <p>Thus far that Gentleman's Letter, and with it an aſſurance that I ambition the Character of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Faithful Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
